hello and welcome everyone to the active
inference Institute this is session one
of the course physics as information
processing with Chris fields
first we'll have Andre Aguirre and Chris
Fields introduce themselves and then
we'll carry on with the first lecture
here check out the video description for
a link to the course overview website
where you can ask questions that will be
answered asynchronously register to
participate in the discussions which
happen about two weeks after each of the
six lecture sessions and just learn more
about this area so thank you both so
much for joining into this adventure we
are starting now and first please Andre
Aguirre introduce yourself and then
Chris introduction and lecture thank you
uh hello so I'll be the course assistant
and
um
specializing in probability and I have a
deep interest in the physics of
information
and I've been uh familiar with Chris's
papers for a while yeah so yeah just
here to learn myself
uh thank you Andrew and thank you Daniel
um I'm Chris fields
and uh I'll be presenting this course in
six sessions
and uh Andrew will be organizing
discussion sessions after each of those
and all of this is explained on the
course website
so uh let's start
this is a course on physics's
information processing
and this first session will be a
historical perspective
on the idea that physics is
is or is about information processing
and I'll just start with a few
quotations that span the middle of the
20th century from Wittgenstein and
1920 saying the world is all that is the
case so defining the world in terms of
facts not objects
a land hour in the early 60s proclaiming
that information is physical
and then uh John Archibald wheeler who
in many ways is the grandfather of this
era recently
um stating it is it from bit so uh
things come from information I.E bit
strings
and if nothing else this shows that that
formulations of this idea get pithier as
the 20th century rolls on
but the history goes uh back further
clearly than the 20th century
that I'm only going to really talk about
a piece of it
and
um the timeline that I'll actually
discuss today the the most relevant
history of this idea
goes back to the mid 19th century
and the first specific
thing I'll talk about is clausius's
definition of entropy
but with the beginning of the
understanding of thermodynamics and the
role of information in thermodynamics
you get this very interesting
multi-disciplinary progression of ideas
that incorporates the beginning of
quantum theory
um
and the the beginning of quantum theory
can kind of be dated to the the first
Solvay conference in 1928 and the famous
debate between Boren Einstein
over whether quantum theory is about
knowledge information or objects things
uh but it incorporates a lot of work in
computer science and logic and
Mathematics so interestingly computer
science
was born effectively in the mid 30s with
the work of church and Turing
which very rapidly converged with the
work in physics so today we'll be
talking about both computer science and
physics
and then in the second half of the 20th
century this just exploded into a huge
area
and in consequence of that mid 20th
century development we're beginning to
see a new idea about physics
which is roughly encapsulated in Quantum
information Theory
and the new idea is this it's that what
physics is actually about
is information transfer across
boundaries
and the information we can represent the
information transfer like this and this
is a conventional use a boundary is
always a blue ellipse
and the Agents that are exchanging
information across this boundary are
conventionally called Alice and Bob
which is just a more polite way of
saying A and B
and when you think about uh this picture
it becomes clear that what physics is
really about is communication
and this is a a wild redescription of
the idea of what physics is compared to
of the ideas of Newton or LaPlace or
even the 19th century ideas
and it's very different from the idea
that's been preserved in
um
20th century physics
in the lineage of Einstein
and others who viewed classical physics
as in a sense of fundamental
um either as completely fundamental or
as a fundamental adjunct to quantum
theory
so this way of thinking about physics
is a very deeply Quantum theoretic way
of thinking about physics
and where we're going in this course uh
today is really
uh the how did this all happen it's the
origin story
and then in the next session I want to
discuss Quantum information Theory
explicitly
and in particular how quantum theory
makes this conclusion that physics is
about communication very simple and
obvious much more obvious than it is in
classical physics
where it takes work to to formulate this
idea
uh then in the next session we're going
to talk about semantics
and how observations become meaningful
to the agents who make them
and hence how actions become meaningful
then in August we'll talk about uh
communication Theory a little bit more
explicitly
and talk about how agents employ
multiple communication channels
when they're communicating
and you know this is this is obvious
when you think of people communicating
they not only talk to each other they
look at the same things they point to
things Etc so this is what I mean by
multiple communication channels
then in September we'll leverage that
discussion to talk about how space-time
actually emerges from communication and
this is one of the most important
aspects I think upon an information
Theory it provides us with a way of
viewing space-time as an emergent
phenomenon
that communication is what is
fundamental
in some ontological sense
and the Box in which it happens face
time is not
so the final session in October will
talk about applications to biology
via the free energy principle and future
directions both in physics and biology
and elsewhere
so it's going to be an interesting ride
I'm keeping
formalism to a minimum uh because we're
directing this toward the broad array of
people who are interested in active
inference
and who are involved with the active
inference Institute
and I would ask you to hold questions
because we have a lot to get through in
an hour
for the interactive discussion and for
the discussion forum
um so uh I hope I explain things well
enough that all of the concepts will be
understandable
uh if not
Wikipedia is actually a wonderful
resource in this area for just
definitions of terms
so if there's anything that that just a
term that is is a trip up uh try
Wikipedia it's probably a very good
source for what these terms mean
so let's start
um our story as I said begins in the
19th century and in the mid 19th century
lots of physicists were devoting their
efforts to figuring out how to make
better steam engines
and
uh one question that arises when you're
trying to design a steam engine is what
happens physically
when you add heat to a system at
constant temperature so if you're
building a steam engine you've got a
boiler because you need to make Steam
and as you turn up the heat to your
boiler
you get more steam but the temperature
doesn't change so this is a mystery uh
what what is the heat actually adding to
the boiler
that is
not increasing the temperature
and
clausius responded to this question in a
way that's sort of typical for a
physicist or a mathematician
since he didn't know what the answer was
he just invented a new name for whatever
it was and gave it a formal definition
so he called it entropy which is a
made-up word that if it was translated
from the Greek would roughly mean
transformation content
in Trophy
and he represented it by a simple
equation that the change in this uh New
Concept entropy which is always called s
is just equal to the change in heat Q
at constant temperature t
so this obviously this equation just
reformulates the question in declarative
form saying whatever this stuff is
uh it's
it's changes in this stuff are just
changes in heated constant temperature
well heat is energy
and this wasn't completely recognized in
the mid 19th century
but the way you'll see this equation in
a current textbook is DS is the it
energy change in energy at constant
temperature
so even more commonly you would see it
written as the change in energy is equal
to the temperature times the change in
the entropy
it's the most common sort of textbook
way of seeing this but the question of
course is what is this quantity what is
this entropy what does this concept mean
and about 15 years after clausius
proposed it boltzmann had the key
insight
which is that entropy is a measurement
of our uncertainty about the state the
system is in
and in particular
oh he again of course went to formalism
and said the entropy s
is equal to some constant
uh times the number of states that the
system can be in that look the same to
us
and since that number of states is
enormous the way to make that manageable
is take to take the log of the number of
states so the natural log is is Ln
and this constant K is called
Boltzmann's constant
and
boltzmann was able to do this because he
subscribed to a radical and very
unpopular Theory
of that material things uh including
gases like air were made of atoms
and heat made the atoms move around
and as you increase the amount of heat
the atoms can move in many different
ways so the number of states that they
can be in that look the same to us
increases and that's what entropy is
it's this increase in the number of
states that the system can be in uh that
all look the same to us with the
measurements that we can make and since
they look the same to us we're uncertain
about exactly what state they're in
so so entropy is a measure of
uncertainty
this was really the beginning of modern
physics
oh because
what it says now
is that decreasing uncertainty requires
energy it links a measurement of
uncertainty to a measurement of energy
and if you think about the uncertainty
principle in quantum theory
how the core idea of the uncertainty
principle is you can't measure a system
without disturbing it
so to actually act on a system requires
energy and that's what you have to do to
get information
so here's boltzmann basically inventing
quantum theory
so we're going to fast forward by
another 15 years to 1900
and in 1900 Planck solved this problem
called the black body radiation problem
which was basically how much heat does
your hot boiler give off into the air
and of all of the measurements of the
heat that hot boilers gave off to the
air ran into problems in classical
physics and caused contradictions and
quantities that went to infinity and all
that was bad so many people were trying
to solve this problem and Planck solved
it by making a simple postulate he said
the energy of the radiation
is proportional to its frequency so its
color in the case of light
and if you go higher frequency you end
up in ultraviolet and x-rays and gamma
rays if you've got a lower frequency you
go into microwaves and radio and all of
that
so this is a nice way of talking about
radiation and it turned out that this
solved the problem I mean just assuming
this simple proportionality relationship
uh produced Spectra for black body
radiation that worked that matched what
you saw experimentally
well this means something very important
it means because this number H the
proportionality constant called Plex
constant is a number it's finite it
means that energy comes in discrete
units of H you can have one H or two H
or 10 million H but you can't have half
an H of energy
um
so it's quantized and this is widely
recognized as the birth of quantum
theory
but of course we should have known this
already if we just thought a little bit
right we know that that changes of
energy
are proportional to the changes in
entropy
uh by temperature
and we know that that entropy is a
measure of the number of states
and numbers of states are just numbers
you can have one state two states three
states 10 million States 100 billion
States but they're all just a number
uh one up
and it's not infinite there's not an
infinite number of states unless you
have an infinite amount of energy which
you don't have
so we knew already that entropy could
only take discrete values
and since energy and entropy are
basically the same thing we knew already
that energy could only take discrete
values
so we could have realized in 1900 that
energy is quantized because the number
of states is quantized
uh so it shouldn't have really been a
mystery why energy was quantitis but it
was a mystery and it stayed a mystery
it's I mean it's in a sits still a
mystery people still debate the meaning
of quantum theory
but another thing we could have known in
1900 was something very important
and it's that this Quantum of action of
Planck's constant which has units of
action which is energy times time
is intimately related to Boltzmann's
constant
uh and Boltzmann's constant has of
units of energy over temperature
but this wasn't actually understood
until the 1950s
no one really figured that this out
there was this relation until the 1950s
and when it was figured out it was
figured out by a guy named Giancarlo
Wick
and he introduced this notion of the
wick rotation
by realizing that if you have an
equation in classical physics
and in it there's the term 1 over KT
you can always replace that one over KT
with this other expression i t over H
bar H bar is just H divided by 2 pi
and you'll get an equation that's valid
in quantum theory
and this is typically described in
textbooks as a trick and whenever
something in physics is described as a
trick what that really means is it's
something we don't understand
uh and lots of papers have been written
about the meaning of the wick rotation
um but to start to understand the wick
rotation
I want to look at this equation a little
bit
of
1 over KT is 1 over in energy
and I T over H bar is 1 over an energy
since h-bar is units of energy times
time
uh we have time in this equation
and then we have this factor I
which is typically thought of as just an
imaginary number so it's the square root
of -1
and what's this I doing in this equation
and in fact you see factors of i t over
H bar if you're familiar with quantum
theory everywhere
in quantum theory
so what's the meaning of this imaginary
number
and
if you just think of i t or or of i as
this arbitrary imaginary number that
somehow renders the equation mysterious
then the whole whole of quantum theory
is mysterious but the wick rotation is
very mysterious
but what I is actually is an operator
and if you think of the real numbers as
an axis which is always drawn
horizontally so here it is here's zero
and the axis is pointing that way I'm
sorry I can't get the camera really far
enough away to see my arm here
so what is I I is actually an operator
that rotates the whole real axis by 90
degrees
so if you if you see a plot of complex
numbers and the real numbers go this way
and the quote imaginary numbers go that
way so what multiplying by I is done is
rotate by 90 degrees
and of course if you do I squared you
rotate twice by 90 degrees my arm will
do this but you end up pointing that way
and those are the negative numbers
so I as an operator that rotates
something by 90 degrees and if you
rotate four times by 90 degrees you're
back to the identity
so I to the fourth is one
so this tells us something very
interesting which is that what the wick
rotation is really talking about is a
rotation
it's a geometrical equation
and in July we'll come back to this and
really probe what this Wick rotation
means physically
um but
as I said this wasn't understood to the
1950s and by the 1950s a lot had
happened
so quantum theory have been developed
boring Einstein had had their debate
particle accelerators had built the
atomic bomb had been built Nuclear
Physics as well in its way
um so
an enormous amount of practical physics
had been done quantum theory was highly
developed people were starting to think
about Quantum field Theory before they
made this this simple realization that's
formulated in the wick rotation
so this is a heartbreaker of things to
come
but before we continue in physics we
need to backtrack and time a little bit
and look at what the mathematicians were
doing
so across the hall in the math
department one year after the Solvay
conference in 1929 uh Kurt girdle proved
his famous first in completeness theorem
and the theorem states that no formal
system that contains arithmetic can be
both consistent and complete
and that means that either there are
true statements that aren't provable in
the in the formal system
or there are false statements that are
provable or of course both
and girdles
proof is is actually extremely simple
almost all of the work in the proof
is setting up all of the notation and
procedures and so forth to formulate
within arithmetic
uh the sentence this sentence is not
provable
and once you have that sentence
formulated within arithmetic then the
conclusion of the proof is is obvious
you know if you can prove the sentence
this sentence is not provable then
you've proved something that's false
and if you can't prove it then there's
then there's sentences that you can't
prove uh in arithmetic
so this was incredibly bad news for
mathematicians
who thought that finite discrete
operations which is what proofs are and
also what computations are can
exhaustively enumerate the facts and
this was the Assumption behind
wittgenstein's claim that
the world is all that is the case the
world is a collection of facts
and optimistically he thought that first
order logic would allow us to enumerate
all those facts and we'd be done
dreams of a final Theory again
um so so girdles there means that no
system with finite capabilities no
system that can just do find out
discrete operations can fully describe
its environment it will always be in an
environment where there are two things
that aren't provable or false things
that are provable
but I think more relative to a
discussion of Agents is that it means
that no agent can describe itself uh any
agent's theory of itself
will either contain true statements that
it can't derive
or false statements or it will either
mystery statements that it can't derive
or it will end up deriving things that
are false about itself
of course we see this in Psychology all
the time
so an immediate consequence of girdle's
theorem was an intense investigation of
what computation actually is what it
meant to talk about finite discrete
operations
and two leaders of this were of course
church and Turing and here's a picture
of a turing machine which is just a
little device with a couple of tapes and
a tape reader and a simple logic unit
that either writes or one or a zero if
it sees a one or a zero
and they defined a computation
as a process that can be implemented in
finite Time by such a machine or by
Church's Lambda calculus or buy any of
the now hundreds of other methods that
are provably equivalent to a turing
machine
so what does this mean
it means that computation is a physical
process that can be mechanized and it
turns out mechanized in any one of a
huge array of ways
it means that many different
implementations of any computation are
possible so I can do it on a turing
machine I can do it on my laptop I can
do it in my head Etc
the most important things it means is
that there are questions with no
computable answer this is the Revenge of
girdle's theorem
and two of the most famous questions of
this kind are given some arbitrary
program will it halt will it will it get
to an answer in finite time and that the
answer to that question is this is
undecidable
no procedure can figure this out
and the other the other
undecidable question
is given some arbitrary program what
function does it compute
and you'd think that would be simple
that you can read a program and figure
out what function it computes but it
turns out that is undecidable that
cannot be done by any finite process
so
this was a another body blow to the goal
of of understanding everything with uh
finite discrete processes but it also
set the stage for something new it set
the stage for thinking about an agent
who interacts with a computational
process
by giving it an input and then looking
at its output sometime later
and this of course will look familiar
because I've included the blue ellipse
which is the boundary which these days
we call a user interface
and the user interface just allows some
finite action on the system and then the
ability to observe some finite response
by the system
so we can now ask what can Alice
determine by acting in some finite way
and then making some finite number of
observations I.E
receiving some finite number of outputs
from the system that she's acting on
and the first 20 years of this produced
a large number of answers all of them
negative so to go back to touring he
proved that Alice can't tell what's
implementing the function that she sees
being implemented
uh she can't tell whether a given input
will lead to an output that's the
halting problem
Oh Shannon showed that Alice can't tell
what the inputs mean to the system
of his whole theory of communication is
completely independent of semantics
and his theory of communication actually
accurately describes what Alice can
observe
uh rice is the one who proved that you
can't determine what program is
generating
the outputs
and then Moore proved a very similar
result in a completely different formal
setting of general cybernetics that you
can't tell what process is generating
the outputs by finite observation
look what Alice can do is build a
predictive model of what generates the
output she sees in response to her
inputs and test it by designing new
inputs
and this is of course as as Carl popper
told us the process that we call science
so owls can do science even though she
can't answer any of these fundamental
questions
now this of course has a huge
technological consequence
uh
since
this theory of computation tells us that
processes are effectively virtual
uh we we don't know what they are and we
can't determine what they are except in
theory by making the theory
uh technologically it means we're free
to use virtualization everywhere because
we have to deal with it anyway
and this allows us to build multi-level
architectures it means that we can
architect computers where no layer of
the computation has any idea what's
going on below or above it and doesn't
need to
uh and that's what makes practical
programming possible so from these no-go
theorems that tell you what you can't do
you actually get an enormous boost into
it
and use
to probe the world and develop theories
and on and on and on
so in a sense girdle birthed not only
computer science but practical Computing
by showing us that virtualization is
just the way the world works so now
let's go back to physics
where these ideas were were
replicated basically reintroduced
reinvented by Feynman
in developing his path integral
formulation of quantum theory
and basically what Hyman realized was
that in any physical process
of The Observer Alice prepares some
state that she's interested in she
prepares some input to an experiment
then she lets something happen
and then she sees what the result of the
experiment is
and the canonical experiment in physics
is scattering you you you know fire two
protons at each other and they intersect
someplace and stuff comes out and you
measure this stuff that comes out
and
what you can measure is momentum and
spin energy things like that position
so
these processes
conserve the total values of the things
you can measure so in particular they
preserve momentum and angular momentum
and they preserve you know other things
that
that are harder to measure and are only
approximately conserved anyway like
lepton number
uh but feynman's contribution to this
way of thinking about experiments was to
say look if you want to understand the
output
you have to sum over all of the possible
processes that could have produced the
output from the input no matter how
improbable they are
so the the famous idea for refinement
diagrams is if you have an electron
that's scattering off an atom
oh you measure the initial state of the
electron that you've generated with an
accelerator or something and you measure
the final state which involves momentum
and spin and so forth and for all you
knew
uh part way through the process the
electron disappeared and an entire
universe appeared and then annihilated
with a copy of an entire anti-universe
and the electron came back out
uh and you have to include processes
like that if you really want to
understand and correctly predict the
outcomes of your measurements
and uh Murray Galvan
lifted does the bumper sticker slogan
from th White and The Once and Future
King everything not explicitly forbidden
is mandatory that sums up feynman's idea
and this is called the totalitarian
principle since it's what's written in
th White's book on the kingdom of the
ants for which everything not explicitly
forbidden is mandatory
so let's think about a real example uh
that's a bit uh actually it's the same
as scattering the ultimate scattering
experiment
uh in physics is a black hole
uh stuff goes into the Horizon of stars
whole galaxies whatever
something happens
and stuff comes out and what comes out
is hawking radiation
and
uh information is conserved if the
information in the Hawking radiation is
actually the same as the information and
the stuff that went in
and conservation is not qualitative it's
quantitative it's only the quantity of
information that's supposed to be
preserved
and you can ask how much
is the information that's being emitted
by a black hole that's emitting Hawking
radiation
and beckenstein was the one who figured
this out using an incredibly simple
argument
but I'll just give the answer here the
answer is that the total entropy of the
black hole
is its area divided by four
and the area in this equation has to be
computed in Planck units which are units
where Planck's Constant and the speed of
light in Boltzmann's Constant and other
interesting things are all set equal to
one
so one plank area is the plank length
squared which turns out to be about 10
to the minus 70th meters squared
so this says that black holes are the
most entropic entities we know of
so a black hole about this big
with a radius of about a meter as an
entropy of about 10 to the 70th
which is of course an astonishingly big
number
and uh a black hole uh
with the area of the Sun so a moderate
sized cosmological black hole a real
thing that we can observe with you know
a gravity wave telescope or something
has an entropy of about 10 to the 79th
and really big black holes which are
bigger than the entire solar system have
entropies into the 10 to the 80th
uh you know 10 to the 85th or something
so these are enormously entropic
entities
um
but beckenstein didn't just tell us that
he told us something about the structure
of the interface The Horizon of a black
hole
and this is what he told us
oh
you can compute entropy and debts just
by using uh
log Space 2 instead of logs based e
natural logs
and that's just inter me multiplying the
natural log by about 1.4
so
we can write the entropy of black hole
of black hole in units of bits and it's
about a over six
so what does this mean to say that we
can think of the entropy in terms of
bits
what it says is that we can think of the
interface
in terms of a bit array
and we can think of all of these bits
as encoded on
this interface
at a density of one bit every roughly uh
six plank lengths of squared six plank
areas so this is an incredibly dense
encoding in a black hole
oh and it's and it's an interesting idea
about black holes but what gets really
interesting is what happens when you
generalize it and of course physicists
are run to generalization and that's
what happened next
um
uh Gerard to hooft almost immediately
thereafter on the basis that beckon's
team's work formulated the holographic
principle
and what the holographic principle says
is we can think of any
system is approximately a black hole
oh and the only approximation is the
encoding density
of the boundary of any system
encodes the information that we can get
about the system
uh at some density and the density is
less than the density for a black hole
because we're not black holes
uh and this rules out a lot by limiting
the amount of information that you can
extract from a system
to the amount of information that you
can actually write on its boundary
and one of the things that it rules out
is knowing the geometry on the inside of
the system and to put it this way which
I I think is a brilliant thought
experiment he says look
the metric inside this system can be so
curved
effectively the space time inside the
system is can be so curved that you
could stick an entire universe inside
and we never know because it wouldn't
change the amount of of entropy the
number of bits that are encoded on the
boundary
so the inside geometry can be anything
and you can't find out by looking at the
outside of the system
now the holographic principle
almost follows from classical physics oh
there's
Euler's theorem which which tells you
about 1 over r squared forces
and you can think of the forces
penetrating the boundary at some
density
and the difference between
Euler's theorem and the holographic
principle is just that the density in
classical physics can go to Infinity
and in the holographic principle it can
only go to this maximal density that's
achieved by a black hole
why because if you try to get any higher
and more information the information
gets sucked into the black hole and you
can't get it out
um
so the holographic principle
becomes a guiding principle for thinking
about any physical system
and what it means to extract information
from a physical system
and in fact we'll talk about this next
time you can say exactly what the
information encoded on the boundary of
any system is
of and uh well I'll go through next time
is is seeing that uh the information
that's encoded on the boundary is a
specification of the the energy that's
being exchanged by the by the
interaction which of course is linear in
the number of bits it's just counting
the number of bits
okay
so
with the holographic principle we now
have a complete new science about
systems that are exchanging
of finite discrete information across a
boundary by encoding that information on
the boundary and then reading the
information off the boundary
so here's a new way of thinking about
physical interaction
Alice writes a message on her boundary
with Bob
and Bob reads the message
off the boundary
and then writes his own new message
which Alice then reads and of course
that's what's happening right now
I'm writing information by speaking
on an interface which is effectively the
internet and you're reading that
information off the internet by
listening to it and when we get time for
questions you'll be writing information
on the internet which I'll be reading
now the key thing about this new science
is that it's topological it's about
connectivity
across some Communication channel which
we represent as a boundary it's not
geometric
so it doesn't assume anything about
space-time
so it allows us to
build a model of space in particular as
an emergent phenomenon
and it allows us to seek time as not
some absolute external abstraction
but something that the communicating
agents measure for themselves
and so they each Act in their own time
and we get a very natural measure of
time in terms of how many bits I see
coming across my boundary and again
we'll talk about that in the next couple
of sessions
um and then
talk about it more thoroughly in
September when we talk about emergent
SpaceTime
so Quantum information Theory looks very
different from the physics that came
before
not because it's adopted a new formalism
of the tools of quantum theory it's
because it's entirely changed the
thinking about what physics is and what
it's about
oh and replace this idea of forces and
balls banging into each other and all of
that with the idea of communication
between agents
and
of course that's familiar from an active
inference perspective
so we can now uh back up a little bit to
see what they were doing in classical
physics during this period well let me
let me go on a little bit sorry
um
this is this is just a slight quoting uh
wheeler
who of course is the most radical in
terms of empathiest in terms of
formulating these ideas
but here's his characterization of this
new physics uh it's not reductive
uh all of the reasoning is circular
you don't have smaller things and then
yet smaller things and then yet smaller
things forever
there are no laws
uh
so what you see on the interface uh is a
is a message it's not something that's
governed by laws since the beginning of
the universe
uh there's no Continuum so there's no
there's nothing described by real
numbers it's all described by integers
everything's done in finite dimensional
spaces
and finally and most importantly there's
no space-time box in which things happen
so think of how radical this is
means there's no big bang
there's no big rip
there's no bouncing universe
all of those ideas are out the window
because they're classical and they're
about space-time
and what the new physics wants to do is
derive space-time out of basically users
experiences
so the the agents here are all Observer
participants in wheelers uh language but
what that just means is Agents
that that want to communicate and it's
their communication that gives rise to
physics
so now we'll go back to classical
and uh what was happening or one thing
that was happening in classical physics
at that time was a lot of thinking about
uh stochastic causal Networks
and um Pearl
realize that if you have any stochastic
causal Network that's unidirectional
then around any node you can draw what
he called a Markov blanket
and a Marco blanket is just the set of
nodes in the network that that
absorb all outside causation and then
transmit that causation into whatever
node you're interested in
and that absorb all causation coming
from the node you're interested in and
transmit it to
the rest of the world
and so we can redraw that in part D here
and it should look very familiar a
Markov blanket is just a classical
physics way of talking about a
holographic screen
and the number of nodes in the Markov
blanket or in particular the number of
degrees of freedom times the number of
nodes is just the number of bits that
flow across that Markov blanket so it's
the number of it's the entropy of the
effective holographic screen
so so this this all these ideas were
reinvented more or less independently
within classical physics
and it was from this classical physics
background
that uh Carl Preston came up with the
idea that a motor called blanket defines
a persistent
at least from an active inference
Institute point of view everyone is
familiar with because it's the
foundation of the idea of active
inference oh
any system
is that persists through time
uh does so by making sure that it
doesn't dissolve into its environment
what does that mean it means it it
persists Through Time by maintaining the
Integrity of its Markov blanket or the
Integrity of its boundary
so this of course is just a tautology
but it's a very it's a very interesting
and very productive tautology
because it says that any System is using
the information it gets on its boundary
from its environment to build a model of
how its environment behaves
and then
it uses that model to act back on its
environment to test and refine its model
and again as popper to told us this is
just what science is
so what the free energy principle really
tells us is that all systems are agents
that are doing science all the time
so physics is effectively uh not just
the study of communication
but it's the study of uh agents doing
science with each other pairs of agents
who are trying to figure each other out
by their communication and communicative
exchanges
so
that's the history of how we got from
1930s sorry 1850s thermodynamics
to the free energy principle
and
how the free energy principle connects
to these very deep and extremely radical
especially within context
ideas in quantum theory and Quantum
cosmology and computer science all of
which tell us
that
the world we see
is a projection that's being written on
our boundaries
by a process that we have no access to
accept the the procedure of active
inference or the procedure of science
which is to formulate predictive models
and test them by doing things in the
world
and seeing how the world responds
so uh that's it for this session
of
the first discussion session which
Anders going to lead will be the 3rd of
June at this same time uh I.E five
o'clock European Time
and then uh my session number two will
be in mid-june
and uh if you look at the course website
uh there's this subsidiary website for
interactive q a
and I invite everyone to post questions
and uh discuss them
and hope that we'll have an interesting
Exchange
and that
[Music]
um
everyone will come to sort of an
understanding of what uh was talked
about today through discussion
and will be uh interested in being back
in June to see how to formulate this in
quantum theory so thank you very much
and and thank you again Daniel for
organizing this and hosting it and
putting together all the technical
things necessary to pull this off
I could never do that on my own
what
thank you we're really
um excited here
any closing thoughts or or Andrew I'd
love to hear your reflection just
briefly what
how would you have told that history or
how does that history reflect on the
areas that you're familiar with
well I I don't think that had much to do
on I
um
I've been you know mainly interested in
the week rotation part I I'm excited to
hear more about that Chris
uh but no I mean I I promise to be a
very very nice summary I don't think I
I'm less familiar with the
with a stop on on computation formal
computation despite being a
mathematician by training
um and
and it was a little more familiar with
with all the physics stuff but yeah
I thought it was great
thank you all right thank you I will uh
close it so in about two weeks we'll
have the first discussion everyone's
welcome to join I will uh share with
Hunter and Chris the questions and we
can develop that and we'll have that on
the course front end um before the
coming discussion so thanks again
fellows see you next time
thank you